<PAGE>
  <TITLE> Statistical Mechanics </TITLE>
  <DESCRIPTION>
     Statistical mechanics is a formalism that aims to explain the physical properties of matter at the
     macroscopic level by considering the dynamical behaviour of matter's microscopic constituents - atoms and molecules.
     The scope of the formalism is almost unlimited as it is applicable to matter in any state of aggregation,
     ranging from gases, liquids and solids to matter in equilibrium with radiation and biological specimens.
     The aim of this course is to introduce the basic principles and methods of statistical mechanics and to
     apply them to a number of model systems in order to illustrate their use and potential in a systematic manner.
     
     We start by introducing the fundamentals of thermodynamics and then proceed to develop the concepts
     and techniques needed to evaluate probability distributions and partition functions. This later quantity
     establishes the link between the microscopic description of a system, based on quantum states or positions in phase space,
     and the macroscopic characterisation provided by a small set of independent thermodynamic variables.  We discuss a number 
     systems where the partition function can be calculated exactly and then show how we can use this function to rationalise 
     the behavior of the constituent particles in these system at the microscopic and macroscopic scales.  Ultimately, however,
     the exact solution for the partition function cannot be found for the majority of real systems of interest.  In the last
     part of the course we therefore discuss how approximate ensemble averages are found by exploiting approximations or numerical
     simulation techniques.
  </DESCRIPTION>
  <AIMS> 
    <UL>
      <LI> You should be able to state the laws of thermodynamics and explain what physical consequences these laws have on the behavior of matter by deriving the Maxwell relations and inequalities involving response functions. </LI> 
      <LI> You should be able to explain how exact solutions for the partition function for a number of model Hamiltonians can be derived.  You should then be able to use these exact solutions to explain how the the component particles in these systems behave when the thermodynamic variables are changed. </LI>
      <LI> You should be able to explain how the mean field and cluster expansion approximations work and how these techniques can be used to calculate approximate partition functions for interacting systems. </LI>
      <LI> You should be able to explain how ensemble averages for interacting systems can be calculated approximately by using Monte Carlo integration or molecular dynamics.  You should be able to explain the limitations of this approach and discuss how these limitations can be overcome by making use of bias potentials. </LI>
    </UL>
  </AIMS>
  <CHAPTER> 
     <TITLE> Classical thermodynamics </TITLE>
     <INTRO>
        <DESCRIPTION>
           In this chapter you will learn about classical thermodynamics. 
        </DESCRIPTION> 
        <AIMS>
           <UL>
              <LI> Something </LI>
           </UL> 
        </AIMS>
     </INTRO>
     <PROJECT>
        <TITLE> </TITLE>
        <DESCRIPTION>
        </DESCRIPTION>
     </PROJECT>
     <TOPIC> THERMODYNAMIC_VARIABLES </TOPIC>
     <TOPIC> GIBBS_PHASE_RULE </TOPIC>
     <TOPIC> EXACT_DIFFERENTIALS </TOPIC>
     <TOPIC> CARNOT_CYCLE </TOPIC>
     <TOPIC> LAWS_OF_THERMODYNAMICS </TOPIC>
     <TOPIC> THERMODYNAMIC_POTENTIALS </TOPIC>
     <TOPIC> MAXWELL_RELATIONS </TOPIC>
     <TOPIC> RESPONSE_FUNCTIONS </TOPIC>
  </CHAPTER>
  <CHAPTER>
     <TITLE> Statistical mechanics applications </TITLE>
     <INTRO>
        <DESCRIPTION>
           In this chapter you will begin to learn about statistical mechanics.  Before delving too deeply into the theory you will do some computer programming 
           exercises that will help you better understand the terminology and methods of statistical mechanics.  You will be introduced to a number of simple 
           Hamiltonians for lattice systems and will learn how to calculate ensemble averages and partition functions for these systems using both analytic methods
           and numerical methods.  The principle aim of these exercises is to get used to the notion of a microstate and the notion that the state of the system 
           includes information on the probability of being in each microstate.
        </DESCRIPTION>
        <AIMS>
           <UL>
              <LI> You should be able to write computer programs to generate all possible microstates for a system consisting of particles on a lattice. </LI>
              <LI> You should be able to write computer programs that evaluate the Hamiltonian for interacting and non-interacting particles on a lattice. </LI>
              <LI> You should be able to evaluate the canonical partition function and the ensemble average of the energy for systems consisting of a small number of interacting or non-interacting particles on a lattice both by writing a computer program.  You should also be able to discuss why this approach fails when the number of particles in the system is large. </LI>
              <LI> You should be able to write computer programs to evaluate histograms and correlation functions. </LI> 
              <LI> You should be able to evaluate the partition function and ensemble average for a system of non-interacting particles on a lattice analytically. </LI>
              <LI> You should be able to explain how mean field theories can be used to approximate the Hamiltonian for systems of interacting particles. </LI> 
           </UL>
        </AIMS>
     </INTRO>
     <PROJECT>
        <TITLE> Two dimensional Ising model </TITLE>
        <DESCRIPTION>
            Write a function to evaluate the Hamiltonian for a two dimensional Ising model.  Use your function and what you have learnt from the exercises on the one-dimensional
            lattice models to evaluate:
              <UL>
                <LI> The ensemble average of the energy as a function of temperature. </LI>
                <LI> Two histograms showing the probability of having various values for the total magnetization at two temperatures </LI>
                <LI> Two correlation functions that show how the correlation between pairs of spins changes with the distance between the two spins investigated.  You should do this exericse twice as you should calculate these correlation functions at two different temperatures. </LI>
             </UL>
            For the correlation function exercise remember that in two dimensions the number of spins at a distance $r$ from a central spin increases as you increase $r$.  
            When you calculate your correlation function you will need to introduce suitable corrections for this effect.
        </DESCRIPTION>
     </PROJECT>
     <TOPIC> LATTICE_GAS </TOPIC>
     <TOPIC> ISING_MODEL </TOPIC>
     <TOPIC> CANONICAL_ENSEMBLE </TOPIC>
     <TOPIC> MEAN_FIELD_MODELS </TOPIC>
  </CHAPTER>
  <CHAPTER>
     <TITLE> Statistical mechanics theory </TITLE>
     <INTRO>
        <DESCRIPTION>
           In this chapter you will learn the theoretical underpinnings of the statistical thermodynamics that you started to study in the previous chapter more rigorously.
           You will learn about the principle of equal apriori probabilities that underpins this theory and about the relationship between the entropy in statistical 
           mechanics and the information in information theory.  You will then learn how we can construct a generalized partition function by performing a constrained 
           optimization of the information.  You will then see how we can use this generalized ensemble to construct thermodynamic ensembles that can be used to describe 
           systems that are under a variety of different constraints on intensive and extensive quantities.  To consolidate all that you have learnt you will learn how we
           can create models that describe interacting and non-interacting gases and adsorption of molecules on surfaces.  Lastly, you will learn about the statistical 
           mechanics of first and second order phase transitions. 
        </DESCRIPTION>
        <AIMS>
           <UL>
              <LI> You should be able to state the principle of equal apriori probabilities. </LI>
              <LI> You should be able to state Khinchines axioms for information theory and you should be able to use these axioms to derive an expression for the information content of a probability distribution. </LI>
              <LI> You should be able to derive an expression for the probability of being in a particular microstate in the generalized ensemble by performing a constrained optimization of the information using Lagrange's method of undetermined multipliers. </LI>
              <LI> You should be able to write out expressions for being in a microstate in the canonical, microcanonical, isothermal isobaric and grand canonical ensembles. </LI>
              <LI> You should be able to derive the equation of state for an ideal gas by first calculating the canonical partition function.  You should also be able to explain the assumptions that are made about the particles of which the gas is composed in this model. </LI>
              <LI> You should be able to explain the equipartition principle and when this partition can be applied. </LI>
              <LI> You should be able to derive the Langmuir adsorption isotherm. </LI> 
              <LI> You should be able to discuss how the microscopic coordinates of the particles behave when a system undergoes a phase transition. </LI>
           </UL>
        </AIMS>
     </INTRO>
     <PROJECT>
        <TITLE> Understanding phase transitions </TITLE>
        <DESCRIPTION>
           We can introduce a very simple model for the transition between a fluid and a gas phase of some substance as follows.  $N$ indistinghisable particles are
           allowed to move freedly on a two dimensional squarre lattice with $V$ sites (where $1 \ll N \ll V$).  The particles are subject to a short ranged attractive
           interaction, which makes the energy of the system $E$ equal to $-\epsilon$ times the number of particle pairs of neighbouring lattice sites.  The kinetic energy
           of the particles is completely neglected in this model. In the fluid phase the particles condense into a single connected block, while in the gas phase the particles
           are distributed randomly on the lattice.

           <UL>
              <LI> Write a program to generate all the possible microstates for a version of this model with 16 lattice sites and 4 particles. Calculate the energies of all these microstates and hence draw a graph showing how the ensemble average of the energy changes with temperature. Discuss the behavior you observe. </LI>
              <LI> Calculate the histogram showing the most likely configurations that this system will adopt at two distinct temperatures </LI>
              <LI> Give a justification for why the free energy of the fluid and gas phases are -$2N\epsilon$ and $-k_B TN \ln \frac{V}{N}$ respectively.  Try to determine the temperature at which the transition between the fluid and the gas phase takes place. </LI>
              <LI> Discuss how this system would behave if the interactions between particles where turned off.  </LI> 
              <LI> Discuss how this model could be extended to provide a model of adsorbtion which, unlike the Langmuir adsorption isotherm, incorporates the interactions between adsorboed molecules.  Perform simulations to explore how such a system would behave for a range of different temperatures and chemical potentials. </LI>
           </UL>
        </DESCRIPTION>
     </PROJECT>
     <TOPIC> PRINCIPLE_OF_EQUAL_APRIORI_PROBABILITIES </TOPIC>
     <TOPIC> INFORMATION_THEORY </TOPIC>
     <TOPIC> LAGRANGE_MULTIPLIERS </TOPIC>
     <TOPIC> GENERALIZED_PARTITION_FUNCTION </TOPIC>
     <TOPIC> PARTITION_FUNCTION_FOR_MOLECULES </TOPIC>
     <TOPIC> ISOTHERMAL_ISOBARIC_ENSEMBLE </TOPIC>
     <TOPIC> GRAND_CANONICAL_ENSEMBLE </TOPIC>
     <TOPIC> ADSORPTION </TOPIC>
     <TOPIC> IDEAL_GAS </TOPIC>
     <TOPIC> PHASE_TRANSITIONS </TOPIC>
     <TOPIC> CLUSTER_EXPANSION </TOPIC>
   </CHAPTER>
  <CHAPTER>
     <TITLE> Computer simulations </TITLE>
     <INTRO>
        <DESCRIPTION>
           In this chapter you will learn about statistical thermodynamics.
        </DESCRIPTION>
        <AIMS>
           <UL>
              <LI> Something </LI>
           </UL>
        </AIMS>
     </INTRO>
     <PROJECT>
        <TITLE> </TITLE>
        <DESCRIPTION>
        </DESCRIPTION>
     </PROJECT>
     <TOPIC> MONTE_CARLO </TOPIC> 
     <TOPIC> MOLECULAR_DYNAMICS </TOPIC>
     <TOPIC> ENHANCED_SAMPLING </TOPIC>
  </CHAPTER>
</PAGE>
