<PAGE>
  <TITLE> Bayes theorem and independence </TITLE>
  <HEADER>
     <script src="assets/scripts/plottingTools.js" type="text/javascript"> </script>
  </HEADER>
  <WELCOME>
     This exercise is going to teach you about Bayes Thoerem and what it means when we say that random variables are independent.  To do this we are going to consider how to answer the following questions:  Consider a test to detect a disease that 10 % of the population have.  The test is 99 % effective in detecting an infected person.  However, the test gives a false positive result in 5 % of cases.  If a person tests positive for the disease what is the probability that they actually have it? 

     We are going to solve this problem by thinking about a stream of patients coming to see a doctor who administers the test.  The probability that each patient has the test will be a random variable and the probability that each patient gets a positive result in the test will also be a random variable.  The probability distributions for these random variables are given in the statement of the problem.
  </WELCOME>
  <WORKSPACE>
    <table> 
      <tr>
        <td>
          <div id="graph" style="width: 400px"></div>
        </td>
        <td width="10px"> nbsp;nbsp; </td>
        <td rowspan="2">
          <div id="blocklyDiv" style="height: 400px"> </div>
        </td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </WORKSPACE>
  <APIFUNCTIONS>
    // Add graph functions to API
    addGraphFunctionsToApi( interpreter, scope );
  </APIFUNCTIONS>
  <BLOCKS>
  </BLOCKS>
  <SCRIPTS>
    myplot.data = [];

    // Load the Google Chart Tools Visualization API and the chart package.
    if (typeof google == 'object') {
      google.load('visualization', '1', {packages: ['corechart']});
    } else {
      alert('Unable to load Google\'s chart API.\n' +
            'Are you connected to the Internet?');
    }
  </SCRIPTS>
  <STARTUP>
    myplot.data.length = 0;
    myplot.data.unshift(['x', 'y'], [0, 0]);
    myplot.plotGraph('graph','scatter');
  </STARTUP>
  <LEVEL>
    <DESCRIPTION>
       Consider the following statement from the question "10 % of the population have the disease."  Use the blocks
       below to generate 40 random variables that represent each patient visiting the doctor.  These random variables should be equal to one if the patient
       has the disease and they should be 0 otherwise.  Remember that 10 % of the population have the disease.  Plot a graph showing how the fraction of 
       patients visiting the doctor who have the disease changes as the number of patients that the doctor has seen increases.
    </DESCRIPTION>
    <HINT>
       If you think about the statement of the question each person represents a Bernoulli random variable. This random variable is one if the patient has the disease and zero otherwise. 
    </HINT>
    <TOOLBOX>
      <category name="Variables" custom="VARIABLE"></category>
      <category name="Program">
         <block type="controls_repeat_ext"></block>
         <block type="math_arithmetic"></block>
         <block type="math_number"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Logic">
        <block type="controls_if"></block>
        <block type="logic_compare"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Random">
         <block type="uniform_random"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Plotting">
         <block type="draw_point"></block>
      </category>
    </TOOLBOX>
    <FINISH>
      prand = 0;
      for(var i=0; i &lt; ww.length; i++ ){
           if( ww[i]=="uniform random variable between 0 and 1" ){ prand += 1; }
      }
      levelcomplete=true;
      if( prand != 1 || myplot.data.length &lt; 3 ){ levelcomplete=false; }
      for(var i=2; i &lt; myplot.data.length; i++ ){
           if( myplot.data[i][0]!=(i-1) || myplot.data[i][1]-Math.floor(myplot.data[i][1])!=0  ){ levelcomplete=false; }
      }
    </FINISH>
  </LEVEL> 
  <LEVEL>
    <DESCRIPTION>
      Now consider the following statement from the question "the test is 99 % effective in detecting an infected person."  This means that when an infected person
      comes to see the doctor the test will give a positive result in 99 % of cases.  Use the blocks below to calculate the number of positive test results the doctor
      will obtain from diseased individuals when he tests 40 patients.  Plot a graph showing how the number of patients visiting the doctor who have the disease
      and who have a positive test result changes as the number of patients that the doctor has seen increases.  Note down the number of final number of patients who 
      get a positive result for the test because they have the disease that you obtain by performing this exercise. 
    </DESCRIPTION>
    <HINT>
      Again the key to answering the question here is realising that we are just dealing with Bernoulli random variables.  The first of these tells us whether the patient has the disease or not.  What does a value of zero mean for the second of these two random variables? 
    </HINT>
    <TOOLBOX>
      <category name="Variables" custom="VARIABLE"></category>
      <category name="Program">
         <block type="controls_repeat_ext"></block>
         <block type="math_arithmetic"></block>
         <block type="math_number"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Logic">
        <block type="controls_if"></block>
        <block type="logic_compare"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Random">
         <block type="uniform_random"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Plotting">
         <block type="draw_point"></block>
      </category>
    </TOOLBOX> 
    <FINISH>
      prand = 0;
      for(var i=0; i &lt; ww.length; i++ ){
           if( ww[i]=="uniform random variable between 0 and 1" ){ prand += 1; }
      }
      levelcomplete=true;
      if( prand != 2 || myplot.data.length &lt; 3 ){ levelcomplete=false; }
      for(var i=2; i &lt; myplot.data.length; i++ ){
           if( myplot.data[i][0]!=(i-1) || myplot.data[i][1]-Math.floor(myplot.data[i][1])!=0  ){ levelcomplete=false; }
      }
    </FINISH>
  </LEVEL> 
  <LEVEL>
    <DESCRIPTION>
      Now consider the following statement from the question: "the test gives a false positive result in 5 % of cases."  This means that when an unaffected person 
      comes to see the doctor the test will give a positive result in 5 % of cases even though the patient does not have the diesease.  Use the blocks below to calculate 
      the number of positive test results the doctor will obtain from healthy individuals when he tests 40 patients.  Plot a graph showing how the number of patients 
      visiting the doctor who get a false positive for the test changes as the number of patients that the doctor has seen increases.  Note down the number of final number 
      of patients who get a false positive result for the test and compare this value with the number of patients who had a true positive that you calculated in the previous 
      exercise.
    </DESCRIPTION>
    <HINT>
      This exercise has a similar answer to the previous one.  The second Bernoulli random variable now tells us if a person without the disease gets a positive test result.
    </HINT>
    <TOOLBOX>
      <category name="Variables" custom="VARIABLE"></category>
      <category name="Program">
         <block type="controls_repeat_ext"></block>
         <block type="math_arithmetic"></block>
         <block type="math_number"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Logic">
        <block type="controls_if"></block>
        <block type="logic_compare"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Random">
         <block type="uniform_random"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Plotting">
         <block type="draw_point"></block>
      </category>
    </TOOLBOX>
    <FINISH>
      prand = 0;
      for(var i=0; i &lt; ww.length; i++ ){
           if( ww[i]=="uniform random variable between 0 and 1" ){ prand += 1; }
      }
      levelcomplete=true;
      if( prand != 2 || myplot.data.length &lt; 3 ){ levelcomplete=false; }
      for(var i=2; i &lt; myplot.data.length; i++ ){
           if( myplot.data[i][0]!=(i-1) || myplot.data[i][1]-Math.floor(myplot.data[i][1])!=0  ){ levelcomplete=false; }
      }
    </FINISH>
  </LEVEL> 
  <LEVEL>
    <DESCRIPTION>
      Now combine the results that you obtained in the previous two exercises and generate a graph showing how the estimate of the conditional probability of getting a positive test
      result because the patient actually has the disease changes as the number of patients that the doctor has seen increases.  Just to remind you the full statement of the problem is as follows: consider a test to detect a disease that 10 % of the population have.  The test is 99 % effective in detecting an infected person.  However, the test gives a false positive result in 5 % of cases.  If a person tests positive for the disease what is the probability that they actually have it?
    </DESCRIPTION>
    <HINT>
      The estimate of the conditional probability is just the number of positive results from diseased individuals divided by the total number of positive test results.  Remember not to divide by zero! 
    </HINT> 
    <TOOLBOX>
      <category name="Variables" custom="VARIABLE"></category>
      <category name="Program">
         <block type="controls_repeat_ext"></block>
         <block type="math_arithmetic"></block>
         <block type="math_number"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Logic">
        <block type="controls_if"></block>
        <block type="logic_compare"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Random">
         <block type="uniform_random"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Plotting">
         <block type="draw_point"></block>
      </category>
    </TOOLBOX>
    <FINISH>
      prand = 0;
      for(var i=0; i &lt; ww.length; i++ ){
           if( ww[i]=="uniform random variable between 0 and 1" ){ prand += 1; }
      }
      levelcomplete=true;
      if( prand != 3 || myplot.data.length &lt; 3 ){ levelcomplete=false; }
      for(var i=2; i &lt; myplot.data.length; i++ ){
           if( myplot.data[i][0]!=(i-1) || myplot.data[i][1] &lt; 0 || myplot.data[i][1] &gt; 1  ){ levelcomplete=false; }
      }
    </FINISH>
  </LEVEL>
  <LEVEL>
    <DESCRIPTION>
      Now suppose for the sake of argument that the test was completely useless and that having a positive test result and having the disease were independent events.  Modify the code
      that you have just written to make this the case.  Once again plot a graph showing how the fraction of individuals who get a positive test result because they actually have the disease changes as the number of patients the doctor has seen increases.  What value does this fraction converge to in this particular case?
    </DESCRIPTION>
    <HINT>
      Remember that two random variables are only independent if the value the first random variable takes has no effect on the value the second random variable takes.  In the previous exercises this was clearly not the case.  What modification do you need to make to your code to make this the case?  You should litterally need to change only one number.
    </HINT>
    <TOOLBOX>
      <category name="Variables" custom="VARIABLE"></category>
      <category name="Program">
         <block type="controls_repeat_ext"></block>
         <block type="math_arithmetic"></block>
         <block type="math_number"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Logic">
        <block type="controls_if"></block>
        <block type="logic_compare"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Random">
         <block type="uniform_random"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Plotting">
         <block type="draw_point"></block>
      </category>
    </TOOLBOX>
    <FINISH>
      prand = 0;
      for(var i=0; i &lt; ww.length; i++ ){
           if( ww[i]=="uniform random variable between 0 and 1" ){ prand += 1; }
      }
      levelcomplete=true;
      if( prand != 3 || myplot.data.length &lt; 3 ){ levelcomplete=false; }
      for(var i=2; i &lt; myplot.data.length; i++ ){
           if( myplot.data[i][0]!=(i-1) || myplot.data[i][1] &lt; 0 || myplot.data[i][1] &gt; 1  ){ levelcomplete=false; }
      }
    </FINISH>
  </LEVEL>
  <REVIEW>
     In this exercise you have learnt about Bayes theorem and have hopefully seen what it means when we state that two random events are independent.  To consolidate what you have learnt write a python notebook that solves the problem described in the exercise above using the numerical technique described in the previous exercises.  Remember that this technique is approximate and that as such you should quote error bars around all the expectation values you estimate in this way.  As such in your notebook ensure that you calculate both the expectation values and the associated error bars around these quantities.  Your error bars should represent a 90 % confidence limit.
  </REVIEW>
</PAGE>
