<PAGE>
  <TITLE> Introduction to Bayes theorem </TITLE>
  <VIDEO> https://www.youtube.com/embed/P9pXM6sT7J0 </VIDEO> 
  <UL>
    <LI> 
      For the first problem in the video - the one about the female engineers - is the quantity you are being asked to calculate a conditional or an absolute probability?  
    </LI> 
    <LI> 
      For the female engineers problem you are given two conditional probabilities and one absolute probability.  What are these the probabilities of?
    </LI>
    <LI> 
      For the question about the medical test there are two random variables: there is a Bernoulli random variable that tells you whether you have 
      the disease and a Bernoulli random variable that tells you whether or not the test result was positive.  Are these random variables independent of each other?  Explain your reasoning.
    </LI>
    <LI> 
      Give a statement of Bayes theorem.
    </LI>
    <LI> 
      Suppose you now administered two tests to the patient to determine whether or not they have the disease.  Test A comes up positive in $P(T_1=1|D=1)$ percent of diseased 
      patients and positive in $P(T_1=1|D=0)$ percent of healthy patients.  Test B by contrast comes up positive in $P(T_2=1|D=1)$ percent of diseased patients and positive 
      in $P(T_2=1|D=0)$ percent of healthy patients.  Draw a Venn diagram showing the various possible categories each individual could be in.  If we can calculate the probability 
      that a person has the disease given they had positive results for the two tests using 
      $P(D=1|T_1=1 \wedge T_2=1) = \frac{P(T_1=1|D=1)P(T_2=1|D=1)P(D=1)}{ P(T_1=1|D=1)P(T_2=1|D=1)P(D=1) + P(T_1=0|D=1)P(T_2=1|D=1)P(D=1) + P(T_1=1|D=1)P(T_2=0|D=1)P(D=1) + P(T_1=0|D=1)P(T_2=0|D=1)P(D=1) }$ 
      what further assumption have we made?  How would we use Bayes theorem to calculate this conditional probability with this assumption relaxed?
    </LI>
    <LI> 
      Consider a pair of discrete random variables, $X$ and $Y$, that can both take values between $0$ and $n$.  Use Bayes theorem to derive an expression for the conditional probability 
      $P(X=a|Y=y)$ in terms of the set of absolute probabilities, $P(X=x_j)$, for getting each possible value for $X$ and the set of conditional probabilities $P(Y=y|X=x_j)$ for getting $Y=y$ 
      given that $X=x_j$.  In doing this you will need to use summation notation.
    </LI>
  </UL>
</PAGE>
