<PAGE>
  <TITLE> Estimating probability mass functions and probability density functions </TITLE>
  <HEADER>
     <script src="assets/scripts/plottingTools.js" type="text/javascript"> </script>
  </HEADER>
  <WELCOME>
     This exercise is going to teach you about how we can use the central limit theorem to obtain an estimate of the probability mass/density function.  Use all your notes on these types of random variables and all the resources you can find online as you work through this exercise.  Also make sure that you look at the working python code that is generated from the blocks as ultimately you will want to use this code in your own programs.  
  </WELCOME>
  <WORKSPACE>
    <table>
      <tr>
        <td>
          <div id="graph" style="width: 400px"></div>
        </td>
        <td width="10px"> nbsp;nbsp; </td>
        <td rowspan="2">
          <div id="blocklyDiv" style="height: 800px"> </div>
        </td>
      </tr>
    </table>
  </WORKSPACE>
  <APIFUNCTIONS>
    // Add graph functions to API
    addGraphFunctionsToApi( interpreter, scope );
  </APIFUNCTIONS>
  <BLOCKS>
  </BLOCKS>
  <SCRIPTS>
    myplot.data = [];

    // Load the Google Chart Tools Visualization API and the chart package.
    if (typeof google == 'object') {
      google.load('visualization', '1', {packages: ['corechart']});
    } else {
      alert('Unable to load Google\'s chart API.\n' +
            'Are you connected to the Internet?');
    }
  </SCRIPTS>
  <STARTUP>
    myplot.data.length = 0;
    myplot.data.unshift(['x', 'y'], [0, 0]);
    myplot.plotGraph('graph','scatter');
  </STARTUP>
  <LEVEL>
    <DESCRIPTION>
       This exercise should be revision: Use the blocks below to generate 50 binomial random variables from a distribution with $n=6$ and $p=0.5$.  
       You should plot each of these random variables on the graph.  The $i$th random variable you generate, $X_i$, should be at the coordinate $(i,X_i)$. 
    </DESCRIPTION>
    <HINT>
       Go look at what you did to generate binomial random variables in the exercise on generating different kinds of random variables. 
    </HINT>
    <TOOLBOX>
      <category name="Variables" custom="VARIABLE"></category>
      <category name="Program">
         <block type="controls_repeat_ext"></block>
         <block type="math_arithmetic"></block>
         <block type="math_number"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Logic">
        <block type="controls_if"></block>
        <block type="logic_compare"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Random">
         <block type="uniform_random"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Plotting">
         <block type="draw_point"></block>
      </category>
    </TOOLBOX>
    <FINISH>
      prand = 0;
      for(var i=0; i &lt; ww.length; i++ ){
           if( ww[i]=="uniform random variable between 0 and 1" ){ prand += 1; }
      }
      levelcomplete=true;
      if( prand != 1 &amp;&amp; myplot.data.length &lt; 3 ){ levelcomplete=false; }
      for(var i=2; i &lt; myplot.data.length; i++ ){
           if( myplot.data[i][1]!=0 &amp;&amp; myplot.data[i][1]!=1 &amp;&amp; myplot.data[i][1]!=2 &amp;&amp; myplot.data[i][1]!=3 &amp;&amp; myplot.data[i][1]!=4 &amp;&amp; myplot.data[i][1]!=5 &amp;&amp;myplot.data[i][1]!=6 ){ levelcomplete=false; }
           if( myplot.data[i][0]!=(i-1) ){ levelcomplete=false; }
      }
    </FINISH>
  </LEVEL> 
  <LEVEL>
    <DESCRIPTION>
      Use the blocks below to generate 20 binomial random variables from a distribution with $n=6$ and $p=0.5$.  Each of these random variables
      will take a value of either 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 or 6. Now instead of plotting each of the random variables on the graph I would like you to 
      use the blocks below to count the number of times each of the random variables come up and to plot how these counts of the number times a 
      particular number comes up changes with time. 
    </DESCRIPTION>
    <HINT>
      You will find it useful to create a list with 7 entries.  Each one these entries should be used to count the number of times each value for the random variable appears.  It is important to remember as you do this that the random value can be equal to the integers 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 or 6.  However, due to our natural language of English, the elements in the list are numbered 1st, 2nd, 3rd, 4th, 5th, 6th and 7th.  In addition notice that the plotting tool you have will draw a bar chart for you.   
    </HINT>
    <TOOLBOX>
      <category name="Variables" custom="VARIABLE"></category>
      <category name="Program">
         <block type="controls_repeat_ext"></block>
         <block type="math_arithmetic"></block>
         <block type="math_number"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Logic">
        <block type="controls_if"></block>
        <block type="logic_compare"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Random">
         <block type="uniform_random"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Lists">
         <block type="lists_repeat"> </block>
         <block type="lists_getIndex"></block>
         <block type="lists_setIndex"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Plotting">
         <block type="draw_bar_chart"></block>
      </category>
    </TOOLBOX> 
    <FINISH>
      prand = 0;
      for(var i=0; i &lt; ww.length; i++ ){
           if( ww[i]=="uniform random variable between 0 and 1" ){ prand += 1; }
      }
      levelcomplete=true;
      if( prand != 1 &amp;&amp; myplot.data.length != 9 ){ levelcomplete=false; }
      for(var i=2; i &lt; myplot.data.length; i++ ){
           if( myplot.data[i][0]!=(i-2) || myplot.data[i][1] &gt; 20 || myplot.data[i][1] &lt; 0 || myplot.data[i][1]-Math.floor(myplot.data[i][1])!=0 ){ levelcomplete=false; }
      }
    </FINISH>
  </LEVEL> 
  <LEVEL>
    <DESCRIPTION>
      In the last exercise you should have plotted the number of times each of the random variables came up.  What I would now like you to do is to 
      plot the fraction of times each of the random variables came up in the experiment.  If you do this correctly the sum of all the fractions will 
      be equal to one.
    </DESCRIPTION>
    <HINT>
      How can we turn the number of times each answer came up, which we generated in the last exercise, into the fraction of times a particular number came up?
    </HINT>
    <TOOLBOX>
      <category name="Variables" custom="VARIABLE"></category>
      <category name="Program">
         <block type="controls_repeat_ext"></block>
         <block type="math_arithmetic"></block>
         <block type="math_number"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Logic">
        <block type="controls_if"></block>
        <block type="logic_compare"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Random">
         <block type="uniform_random"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Lists">
         <block type="lists_repeat"></block>
         <block type="lists_getIndex"></block>
         <block type="lists_setIndex"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Plotting">
         <block type="draw_bar_chart"></block>
      </category>
    </TOOLBOX>
    <FINISH>
      prand = 0;
      for(var i=0; i &lt; ww.length; i++ ){
           if( ww[i]=="uniform random variable between 0 and 1" ){ prand += 1; }
      }
      levelcomplete=true; var sum=0;
      if( prand != 1 &amp;&amp; myplot.data.length != 9 ){ levelcomplete=false; }
      for(var i=2; i &lt; myplot.data.length; i++ ){
           sum += myplot.data[i][1];
           if( myplot.data[i][0]!=(i-2) || myplot.data[i][1] &gt; 1.0 || myplot.data[i][1] &lt; 0 ){ levelcomplete=false; }
      }
      if( sum &gt; 1.05 || sum &lt; 0.95 ){ levelcomplete=false; }
    </FINISH>
  </LEVEL> 
  <LEVEL>
    <DESCRIPTION>
       We are now going to repeat the exercise of calculating a histogram that we just performed but we are going to do the exercise for a normal random variable.
       Divide the range between -4 and +4 into 20 intervals of length 0.4 and create a list with one scalar for each or the sub-ranges in this range.  Now use the 
       blocks below to generate 20 random variables from a normal distribution with mean 0 and variance 1.  Use the list that you created to count the number of times
       the random variable falls into each of the sub-ranges.  Once you have generated all the random variables plot a bar graph showing the fraction of times that the 
       random variable fell into each of the intervals of interest on the $y$ axis and the value at the center of the sub-range on the $x$.  
    </DESCRIPTION>
    <HINT>
       In the previous exercise we could use the value of the random variable to determine what element of the list we had to add one to to get our updated histogram.  We cannot do the same here as the random variables we generate are real numbers and not integers.  Notice, however, if we divide the random variable value we generate by 0.4 and if we then round down we do get an integer.   
    </HINT>
    <TOOLBOX>
      <category name="Variables" custom="VARIABLE"></category>
      <category name="Program">
         <block type="controls_repeat_ext"></block>
         <block type="math_arithmetic"></block>
         <block type="math_number"></block>
         <block type="math_round"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Random">
         <block type="uniform_random"></block>
         <block type="normal_random"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Lists">
         <block type="lists_repeat"></block>
         <block type="lists_getIndex"></block>
         <block type="lists_setIndex"></block>
      </category>
      <category name="Plotting">
         <block type="draw_bar_chart"></block>
      </category>
    </TOOLBOX>
    <FINISH>
      prand = 0; 
      for(var i=0; i &lt; ww.length; i++ ){
           if( ww[i]=="standard normal random variable" ){ prand += 1; }
      }
      levelcomplete=true; var sum=0;
      if( prand != 1 &amp;&amp; myplot.data.length != 22 ){ levelcomplete=false; }
      for(var i=2; i &lt; myplot.data.length; i++ ){
           sum += myplot.data[i][1]
           if( myplot.data[i][0]!=(-3.8+(i-2)*0.4) || myplot.data[i][1] &gt; 1.0 || myplot.data[i][1] &lt; 0 ){ levelcomplete=false; }
      }
      if( sum &gt; 1.05 || sum &lt; 0.95 ){ levelcomplete=false; } 
    </FINISH>
  </LEVEL>
  <REVIEW>
     In this exercise you have learnt how we use the central limit theorem and the law of large numbers to estimate probability mass functions and probability density functions 
     from identically distributed and indepedent random variables.  To consolidate what you have learnt write a python notebook that repeats the last exercise above - the estimation of the probability density function for the normal distribution.  Do not update the graph after each new point is generated though as it will make your code very slow.  Instead only plot the histogram once you have generated all the random variables.  Try to work out how to calculate the cumulative probability distribution function from this probability mass function (hint: you will need to integrate the probability density function you estimated numerically).  Try to do this exercise with different numbers of subranges.  In your notes discuss using suitable diagrams how the shape of the cumulative probability distribution function you obtain through this procedure differs from the shape of the true cumulative probability distribution function.
  </REVIEW>
</PAGE>
