<PAGE>
  <TITLE>Finding the stationary distribution of a Markov chain
</TITLE>
  <DESCRIPTION>
The following problems all involve Markov chains with a limiting 
stationary distribution.  The purpose in doing these problems is for you 
to come to understand how to set up the chain 
and how to find the stationary distribution by finding the top eigenvector
of the transition matrix.
</DESCRIPTION>
  <QUESTION_GROUP>
    <EXAMPLE>
      <QUESTION>
A Markov chain is described by the following transition matrix:
$$
 \left( 
 \begin{matrix}
  1 - 4p &amp; 4p &amp; 0 \\
  2p &amp; 1 - 4p &amp; 2p \\
  0 &amp; 2p &amp; 1 - 2p
 \end{matrix}
 \right)
$$
Determine the range of values which $p$ is allowed to take and the 
range of values of $p$ for which the matrix has a limiting stationary
distribution.  Then find the limiting stationary distribution for this
chain.
</QUESTION>
      <SOLUTION>
For the range of values $p$ can take we know that all the elements of the matrix must be positive or zero 
and that the rows of the matrix must sum to one.  As such $0 \le p \le\frac{1}{4}$ 
<br/> <br/>
The chain has a limiting stationary distribution if in the long time limit there probability of being in 
any given state in the future does not depend on the starting state.  This is true for $0 \lt p \le \frac{1}{4}$.
It is not true for $p=0$ as say we start in state 0. We are guaranteed to finish in state 0 as state
0 is only connected to itself.  This is also true for states 1 and 2 - as when $p=0$ the matrix is diagonal. 
The state we end up in the long time limit thus depends on the intial state and there is no limiting stationary distribution.
<br/> <br/>
There are two ways of proceedinghere:
<br/> <br/>
<b> (1) Gaussian Elimination: </b> <br/> <br/>
We want to find the solution, $\pi$ of the following matrix equation:
$$
\pi \mathbf{A} = \pi \qquad \rightarrow \qquad [\mathbf{A}^T - \mathbf{I}] \pi = 0
$$
We do this by Gaussian elimination as follows.  First we reduce the matrix to upper triangular form
as shown below:
$$
[\mathbf{A}^T - \mathbf{I}]  = \left( 
\begin{matrix}
-4p &amp; 2p &amp; 0 \\
4p &amp; -4p &amp; 2p \\
0 &amp; 2p &amp; -2p
\end{matrix}
\right) 
$$
Adding row (1) to row (2) gives:
$$
[\mathbf{A}^T - \mathbf{I}]  = \left(  
\begin{matrix}
-4p &amp; 2p &amp; 0 \\
0 &amp; -2p &amp; 2p \\
0 &amp; 2p &amp; -2p
\end{matrix}
\right)
$$
And now adding row (2) to row (3) gives the an upper triangular matrix:
$$
[\mathbf{A}^T - \mathbf{I}]  = \left(
\begin{matrix}
-4p &amp; 2p &amp; 0 \\
0 &amp; -2p &amp; 2p \\
0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0
\end{matrix}
\right)
$$
We can thus write that:
$$
[\mathbf{A}^T - \mathbf{I}] \pi = 
\left( 
\begin{matrix}
-4p &amp; 2p &amp; 0 \\
0 &amp; -2p &amp; 2p \\
0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0
\end{matrix}
\right) \left(
\begin{matrix}
\pi_1 \\
\pi_2 \\
\pi_3
\end{matrix}
\right) = 0 \qquad \rightarrow \qquad 
\begin{matrix}
-4p \pi_1 + 2p \pi_2 = 0 \\ 
 -2p \pi_2 + 2p\pi_3 = 0
\end{matrix}
\qquad \rightarrow \qquad
\begin{matrix}
2 \pi_1 = \pi_2 \\
\pi_2 = \pi_3 
\end{matrix}
$$
<br/> <br/>
<b> (2) Detailed Balance: </b> <br/> <br/>
We can arrive at the two simultaneous equations above via an alternative route if we use the detailed balance condition.  
Remember this states the elements of the transition matrix, $\mathbf{A}$, and the elements of the limiting stationary distribution, $\pi$, are related by:
$$
\pi_i A_{ij} = \pi_j A_{ji}
$$ 
With our transition matrix:
$$
\mathbf{A} = 
 \left(
 \begin{matrix}
  1 - 4p &amp; 4p &amp; 0 \\
  2p &amp; 1 - 4p &amp; 2p \\
  0 &amp; 2p &amp; 1 - 2p
 \end{matrix}
 \right)
$$
We thus have for states 1 and 2: $\qquad \pi_1 4p = \pi_2 2p \qquad \rightarrow \qquad 2\pi_1 = \pi_2$ <br/> <br/>
And for states 2 and 3: $\qquad \pi_2 2p = \pi_3 2p \qquad \rightarrow \qquad \pi_2 = \pi_3$ <br/> <br/> 
<b> The end of the problem </b> <br/> <br/>
Both the methods described above (Gaussian elimination and Detailed balance) got us to the following equations:
$$
2\pi_1 = \pi_2 \qquad \textrm{and} \qquad \pi_2 = \pi_3 
$$
We thus have two simultaneous equations and two unknowns.  We cannot solve these equations.  We know, however, that 
$\pi$ is a vector of probabilities and that as such this vector must be normalized so that:
$$
\pi_1 + \pi_2 + \pi_3 = 1
$$
We can thus write:
$$
1= \pi_1 + \pi_2 + \pi_3 = \pi_1 + 2 \pi_1 + 2\pi_1 = 5\pi_1 \qquad \rightarrow \qquad \pi_1 = \frac{1}{5} 
$$
Inserting this equation into the equations above gives:
$$
\pi_1 = \frac{1}{5} \qquad \pi_2 = \frac{2}{5} \qquad \pi_3 = \frac{2}{5}
$$
</SOLUTION>
    </EXAMPLE>
  </QUESTION_GROUP>
  <QUESTION_GROUP>
    <EXAMPLE>
      <QUESTION>
Consider the  reversible  Markov chain, between the
states $X=0,1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8$,  represented  by  the following matrix.
$$
P=
\left(
\begin{matrix}
 0&amp; 1/2&amp; 0&amp; 0&amp; 0&amp; 1/2&amp; 0&amp; 0&amp; 0\\ 
 1/3 &amp; 0 &amp;1/3&amp; 0&amp; 1/3&amp; 0&amp; 0&amp; 0&amp; 0 \\
 0&amp; 1/2 &amp;0 &amp;1/2&amp; 0&amp; 0&amp; 0&amp; 0&amp; 0 \\
 0 &amp;0 &amp; 1/3&amp; 0 &amp;1/3&amp; 0 &amp;0 &amp;0 &amp;1/3\\ 
 0&amp; 1/4&amp; 0 &amp;1/4&amp; 0&amp; 1/4&amp; 0&amp; 1/4 &amp;0\\ 
 1/3&amp; 0 &amp;0&amp; 0&amp; 1/3&amp; 0&amp; 1/3&amp; 0&amp; 0 \\
 0&amp; 0 &amp;0 &amp;0 &amp;0 &amp;1/2&amp; 0&amp; 1/2&amp; 0 \\
 0&amp; 0 &amp;0&amp; 0&amp; 1/3 &amp;0 &amp;1/3&amp; 0 &amp;1/3\\ 
 0 &amp;0&amp; 0&amp; 1/2&amp; 0&amp; 0&amp; 0&amp; 1/2&amp; 0   \\
\end{matrix}
\right) \qquad .
$$
Draw the transition graph for this process (hint: start by drawing a 3 x 3 grid
of nodes with 0, 5 and 6 on the top row 1,4 and 7 on the second row and 2,3 and
8 on the bottom row).  Then find the stationary distribution by using the detailed
balance condition.
</QUESTION>
      <SOLUTION>
The transition graph for this particular Markov chain looks like this:
<center> <img src="Images/markov-stat-dist-q2.png" align="middle" width="300"/> </center>
By using the detailed balance condition:
$$
\pi_{i}p_{ij} = \pi_{j}p_{ji}
$$
we can find that the stationary distribution satisfies the following equations:
$$
\pi_0 = \pi_2 = \pi_6 = \pi_8 \qquad \pi_1 = \pi_3 = \pi_5 = \pi_7 = \frac{3}{2} \pi_0 \qquad \pi_4 = 2 \pi_0
$$
When these equations are solved by exploiting the fact that $\pi$ must be normalized we thus find that:
$$
\pi_0 = \pi_2 = \pi_6 = \pi_8 = \frac{1}{12} \qquad \pi_1 = \pi_3 = \pi_5 = \pi_7 = \frac{3}{24} = \frac{1}{8} \qquad \pi_4 = \frac{2}{12} = \frac{1}{6}
$$
</SOLUTION>
    </EXAMPLE>
  </QUESTION_GROUP>
  <QUESTION_GROUP>
    <EXAMPLE>
      <QUESTION>
A double glazing firm employs staff to cold call clients and try to sell
them new windows for their home. There are three levels of staff pay: Level 1
(£50), Level 2 (£75) or Level 3 (£100).  The amount a
person is paid in a given evening is determined by their performance
that evening and their performance on the previous evening.  A staff member who
was paid at level 1 on the previous day is moved to level 2 if they are
amongst the top 80% of sellers that evening. Similarly a staff member on level
2 the previous evening is moved to level 3 if they are amongst the top 80% this evening. Members of staff in the bottom 20% have their pay reduced by
at least one level.  If they are in level 2 their pay falls to that of
level 1.  If they are in level 3 they fall to level 1 if they are in the bottom
5% and level 2 otherwise. If the company employs
$n$ members of staff, calculate the average amount they would expect to pay out
in salaries each evening.  You may assume that the performance of any given
member of the sales team is random and hence that the ordering of
staff performances is random. 
</QUESTION>
      <SOLUTION>
The transition matrix for this problem should be:
$$
A = 
\left(
\begin{matrix}
0.2 &amp; 0.8 &amp; 0.0 \\
0.2 &amp; 0.0 &amp; 0.8 \\
0.05 &amp; 0.15 &amp; 0.8 
\end{matrix}
\right)
$$
You can find the stationary distribution by using Gaussian elimination.  It is:
$$
\pi_1=\frac{1}{11} \qquad \pi_2 =\frac{2}{11} \qquad \pi_3 = \frac{8}{11}
$$
The expected amount you need to pay out each evening is thus:
$$
\textrm{pay} = 90.91n \quad \textrm{pounds}
$$
</SOLUTION>
    </EXAMPLE>
  </QUESTION_GROUP>
  <QUESTION_GROUP>
    <EXAMPLE>
      <QUESTION>
A magazine has print and ipad editions and 100,000 subscribers. These
subscribers can subscribe to the magazine in
one of three ways. They can buy the print magazine only, they can buy an ipad
subscription only or they can buy both an ipad and a print subscription to the
magazine.  The magazine is constantly changing its content and there is not
always a complete overlap between the features in the ipad and print versions of
the magazine.  As a consequence people are continuously changing their
subscription package. In any given week no one ever changes from a
purely print subscription to the ipad edition and vice versa.  However, every
week a constant fraction, $p$, of the subscribers on a print only subscription
change to the ipad+print subscription.  Similarly $p$ subscribers on
an ipad only subscription change to the ipad+print subscription every week. Of
those subscribers on the ipad+print subscription a fraction, $2p$, of them
decide which version of the magazine they prefer in any given week and adjust
their subscription accordingly. Subscribers are split 50/50 on which version of
the magazine they prefer so $p$ change to ipad only, while the other $p$ 
change to print only.  Explain why the level of subscription a person has to
the magazine is a Markov process, draw the transition graph and write down the
transition matrix for the random variable. Calculate the average number of
magazines
that need to be printed each week in order to satisfy the demand for printed
editions.
</QUESTION>
      <SOLUTION>
The transition matrix for this problem should be:
$$
\left( 
\begin{matrix}
1-p &amp; p &amp; 0 \\
p &amp; 1-2p &amp; p \\
0 &amp; p &amp; 1-p
\end{matrix}
\right)
$$
We find the stationary distribution to be:
$$
\pi_1 = \pi_2 = \pi_3 = \frac{1}{3}
$$
The number of magazines required is thus: 66667
</SOLUTION>
    </EXAMPLE>
  </QUESTION_GROUP>
  <QUESTION_GROUP>
    <EXAMPLE>
      <QUESTION>
I own 4 umbrellas and keep some in my home and some in my
office.  I keep moving between my home and office and only take one of my
umbrellas with me if it rains.  Obviously, if it does not rain I do not take an
umbrella. The probability of rain on any given day is equal to $p$. Explain
why the number of umbrellas in my current location, $S$, is a Markov process,
draw the transition graph for this variable and write out the transition matrix.
When doing this remember that if there are 3 umbrellas in my office, $S_i=3$,
and it doesn't rain there will be 1 umbrella available for me once I get home,
$S_{i+1}=1$, and set out to the office once more.  
Now use the Markov chain you have drawn to solve the following problem:  
If I am in my office/home when it rains and there are no
umbrellas available I will get wet as I walk to home/work.  Using the
detailed balance condition or otherwise show that if $p=0.6$ the probability
this will occur is approximately 5.4 %.  How many umbrellas should I buy if I
want the probability of getting wet to be less than 1 %.
</QUESTION>
      <SOLUTION>
The transition matrix in the four umbrella case is:
\[
 \begin{matrix}
  \mathbf{P} = \left( 
  \begin{matrix}
  0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 1 \\
  0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 1-p &amp; p \\
  0 &amp; 0 &amp; 1-p &amp; p &amp; 0 \\
  0 &amp; 1-p &amp; p &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \\
  1-p &amp; p &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 
  \end{matrix}
  \right)
 \end{matrix}
\]
This matrix has an interesting symmetry, which we will exploit in solving the final problem.  At first 
though lets try to determine the stationary distribution (using detailed balance) for the four umbrella
case.  The detailed balance equations tell us that:
\[
\pi_0 = \pi_4( 1-p) \qquad \pi_1 ( 1-p) = \pi_3 (1-p) \qquad \pi_2 p = \pi_3 p 
\qquad \pi_1 p = \pi_4 p
\]
In other words $\pi_1=\pi_2=\pi_3=\pi_4=\frac{1}{1-p}\pi_0$ and, as normalization tells us, we thus have:
\[
 1 = \pi_0 + \pi_1 + \pi_2 + \pi_3 + \pi_4 = (1-p)\pi_1 + 4\pi_1 = (5-p)\pi_1 \qquad \rightarrow \qquad \pi_1 = \frac{1}{5-p}
\]
and hence that:
\[
\pi_0 = \frac{1-p}{5-p}
\]
This probability, $\pi_0$, is the probability that I am in a location where there is no umbrella.  For me to also get
wet it must rain as I walk to home/work.  (I will get wet in these cases as I have no umbrella to take with me on the 
journey).  The probability of getting wet is thus:
\[
 P(\textrm{WET}) = \frac{p(1-p)}{5-p} = \frac{0.6\times 0.4}{4.4} \approx 
0.0545 
\]
Now the nice thing in this question is that the symmetry of the matrix ensures that we can come up with a general equation 
for the result.  That is to say we can come up with a solution if we have $n$ (as opposed to four) umbrellas.  When we construct
the $(n+1) \times (n+1)$ matrix that we would have in this case and exploit the detailed balance condition we would find that:
$$
\pi_1 = \pi_2 = \pi_3 = \dots = \pi_n
$$
Furthermore, just as in the four umbrella question $\pi_0=(1-p)\pi_1$.  Following through the working above (i.e. using the normalisation
condition and so on) we find that:
\[
 P(\textrm{WET}) = \frac{p(1-p)}{n+1-p} \qquad \rightarrow \qquad n = \frac{p(1-p)}{P(\textrm{WET})} - 1 + p
\]
Hence for chance of getting wet to be less than 1% with $p=0.6$ we need:
\[
 n = \frac{ 0.6 \times 0.4 }{ 0.01 } - 0.4 \approx 24
\]
</SOLUTION>
    </EXAMPLE>
  </QUESTION_GROUP>
</PAGE>
