<PAGE>
  <TITLE>Poisson Process Problems</TITLE>
  <DESCRIPTION>
  The problems below provide some further examples of problems that we can solve using this particular 
  continuous time Markov chain.
  </DESCRIPTION>
  <QUESTION_GROUP>
    <EXAMPLE>
      <QUESTION>
         The servers for the email system in a large company store all the emails that are sent or received on a hard drive.
         Once this hard drive fills with data the system administrators must replace the drive.  If no emails arrive during this process this piece of routine
         maintenance takes a total of $c$ hours.  However, this time is extended by an additional $d$ hours if any emails arrive as they are replacing the drive.
         Show that the expected time to replace the hard drive is given by:
         \[
         \mathbb{E}(D) = (c+d) - de^{-\lambda c}
         \]
         if emails arrive in accordance with a Poisson process with a rate of $\lambda$ per hour.  If you are the manager of these engineers how much time should you allocate them to
         complete the job of replacing the drive?
      </QUESTION>
      <SOLUTION>
         As the emails arrive in accordance with a Poisson process the arrival time for the first email, $T$, is an exponentially distributed random variable with parameter $\lambda$
         \[
          P(T \le t ) = 1 - e^{-\lambda t} \qquad \rightarrow \qquad P(T = t ) = 
         \frac{\textrm{d}P(T \le t)}{\textrm{d}t} = \lambda e^{-\lambda t}
         \]
         We can thus calculate the expectated time to complete the job by conditioning on the arrival time of first email.  We have:
         \[
          \mathbb{E}(D) = (c+d)\int_0^c \lambda e^{-\lambda t} \textrm{d}t + c \int_c^\infty \lambda e^{-\lambda t} \textrm{d}t
         \]
         This integral is solved as follows: 
         \[
         \begin{aligned}
          \mathbb{E}(D) &amp; = (c+d)\lambda \int_0^c e^{-\lambda t} \textrm{d}t + c\lambda \int_c^\infty e^{-\lambda t} \textrm{d}t \\
                        &amp; = (c+d)\lambda \left[ -\frac{1}{\lambda}e^{-\lambda t} \right]_0^c + c\lambda \left[ -\frac{1}{\lambda} e^{-\lambda t} \right]_c^\infty \\
                        &amp; = (c+d)[1 - e^{-\lambda c}] + ce^{-\lambda c} \\
                        &amp; = (c+d) - de^{-\lambda c} 
         \end{aligned}
         \]
         It will take the engineers either $c$ hours or $c+d$ hours to complete the job.  The time they take <b> will never</b> be equal to the expectation.  Hence you
         should allocate $c+d$ hours of their time as this is the longer of the two times.
      </SOLUTION>
    </EXAMPLE> 
  </QUESTION_GROUP>
</PAGE>
