<PAGE>
  <TITLE> The canonical ensemble </TITLE>
  <DESCRIPTION>


The canonical ensemble is a statistical model that can be used to describe the behavior of a system 

with a constant temperature, a constant number of atoms and a constant volume.  If we have a Hamiltonian, $H(x,p)$,

for the system the canonical partition function can be calculated using:

$$

Z_c = \sum_i e^{-\beta H(x_i,p_i) }

$$

The sum here runs over all the microstates in the system and is replaced by an integral if you have a continuous

rather than a discrete state space.  $\beta$, meanwhile, is equal to one divided by the temperature, $T$, multiplied by 

Boltzmann's constant, $k_B$.  That is to say $\beta = \frac{1}{k_B T}$.  



The probabibility of being with an individual microstate in the canonical ensemble is given by:

$$

p_i = \frac{ e{-\beta H(x_i,p_i) } }{ Z_c }

$$

We can thus calculate the average energy of the system by computing an emsemble average using:

$$

\langle E \rangle = \sum_i H(x_i,p_i) p_i

$$

or by using the analytical result below:

$$

\langle E \rangle = - \frac{ \partial \ln Z }{\partial \beta }

$$

There is a similar result that we can use to calculate the heat capacity:

$$

C_v = \frac{1}{k_B T^2} \langle ( E - \langle E \rangle )^2 \rangle = \frac{1}{k_B T^2} \left( \frac{ \partial^2 \ln Z }{\partial \beta^2 } \right)

$$ 



  </DESCRIPTION>
  <AIMS>
    <UL>
    <LI>  You should be able to write an expression for the canonical partition function.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to write an expression for the probability of being in a particular micostate if the system has constant number of atoms, constant volume and constant temperature.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to explain how the Helmholtz free energy and the canonical paritition function are related.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to explain how ensemble averages are calculated in the canonical ensemble.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to explain how we can calculate the ensemble average of the energy by taking a derivative of the canonical partition function.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to explain how the heat capacity can be calculated from fluctutations.
 </LI>
    </UL>
  </AIMS>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> CANONICAL_ENSEMBLE </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> VIDEO </LEVEL>
<TYPE> XML </TYPE>
<MODULE> PHY9038/AMA4004 </MODULE>
<LINK> canonical-ensemble-video1 </LINK>
<AUTHOR> G.~Tribello </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
A video in which the canonical ensemble is derived from the generalised partition function
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> CANONICAL_ENSEMBLE </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> VIDEO </LEVEL>
<TYPE> XML </TYPE>
<MODULE> PHY9038/AMA4004 </MODULE>
<LINK> canonical-ensemble-video2 </LINK>
<AUTHOR> G.~Tribello </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
A video which shows how ensemble averages for the energy can be found by taking derivatives of the canonical partition function.
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> CANONICAL_ENSEMBLE </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> READING </LEVEL>
<TYPE> PDF </TYPE>
<MODULE> AMA4004 </MODULE>
<LINK> ensembles-notes.pdf </LINK>
<AUTHOR> G.~Tribello </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
Some notes on the various different thermodynamic ensembles
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
</PAGE>
