<PAGE>
  <TITLE> Conditional expectation </TITLE>
  <DESCRIPTION>


The conditional expectation of a discrete random variable $X$ given that the random variable $Y$ equals $y_i$ is given by:



$$

\mathbb{E}(X|Y=y_i) = \sum_{j=0}^\infty x_j P(X=x_j | Y=y_i )

$$



Conditional expectation values are useful because we can use them to calculate absolute expectation values using the conditional 

expectation theorem:



$$

\mathbb{E}(X) = \sum_{i=0}^\infty \mathbb{E}(X|Y=y_i) P(Y=y_i)

$$



Another useful result that is derived using similar logic involves the fact that the expectation $\mathbb{E}(XY)$ can be calculated as:



$$

\mathbb{E}(XY) = \mathbb{E}(X)\mathbb{E}(Y)

$$



If the random variables $X$ and $Y$ are independent.  This equation does not hold in general when the variables are not independent.



  </DESCRIPTION>
  <AIMS>
    <UL>
    <LI>  You should be able to explain what a conditional expectation value of a random variable measures.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to write out the conditional expectation theorem.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to calculate the mean and variance of the geometric random variable using the conditional expectation theorem.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to explain when the expectation $\mathbb{E}(XY)$ can be calculated as $\mathbb{E}(X)\mathbb{E}(Y)$.
 </LI>
    </UL>
  </AIMS>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> CONDITIONAL_EXPECTATION </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> INTRO </LEVEL>
<TYPE> XML </TYPE>
<MODULE> SOR3012 </MODULE>
<LINK> conditional-expectation-video </LINK>
<AUTHOR> G.~Tribello </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
Using the conditional expectation theorem to calculate the expectation and variance of the geometric random variable
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> CONDITIONAL_EXPECTATION </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> EXERCISE </LEVEL>
<TYPE> XML </TYPE>
<MODULE> SOR3012 </MODULE>
<LINK> conditional-expectation-problems </LINK>
<AUTHOR> G.~Tribello </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
Problems involving using the conditional expectation theorem to calculate expectation values.
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> CONDITIONAL_EXPECTATION </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> INTRO </LEVEL>
<TYPE> PDF </TYPE>
<MODULE> SOR3012 </MODULE>
<LINK> jim-chap07.pdf </LINK>
<AUTHOR> J.~F.~McCann </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
A description of the conditional expectation theorem and an explanation of how it can be used to calculate expectation values.
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
</PAGE>
