<PAGE>
  <TITLE> Markov chains in continuous time </TITLE>
  <DESCRIPTION>


The central equation in the theory of continuous time Markov chains is the Kolmogorov equation:

$$

\frac{\textrm{d} \mathbf{P}(t)}{\textrm{d}t} = \mathbf{P(t)}\mathbf{Q}

$$

In this equation $\mathbf{Q}$ is the so called jump rate matrix, which is the following matrix of limits.

$$

\lim_{\delta t \rightarrow 0} \frac{P(\delta t) - \mathbf{I}}{\delta t}

$$

The first of these two equations has the differential of a matrix of probabilities on the left hand side.  

A continuous time Markov chain thus has a limiting stationary distribution $\pi$ if there is any non-zero 

vector that satisfies:

$$

\pi \mathbf{Q} = 0

$$

This equation comes about by setting $\frac{\textrm{d} \mathbf{P}(t)}{\textrm{d}t}=0$ in the first equation.



  </DESCRIPTION>
  <AIMS>
    <UL>
    <LI>  You should be able to explain why the Chapman-Kolmogorov relation is particularly useful in the context of continuous time Markov chains.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to explain what is meant by the jump-rate matrix for a continuous time Markov chain.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to derive the Kolmogorov relation for continuous-time Markov chains.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to show that the exponential of the jump rate matrix multiplied by time is the solution of the Kolmogorov relation
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to explain what conditions must be satisfied by the jump rate matrix of a continuous time Markov chain in order for it to have a stationary distribution.
 </LI>
    </UL>
  </AIMS>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> CONTINUOUS_TIME_MARKOV_CHAIN </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> INTRO </LEVEL>
<TYPE> PDF </TYPE>
<MODULE> SOR3012 </MODULE>
<LINK> jim-chap23.pdf </LINK>
<AUTHOR> J.~F.~McCann </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
Notes on Markov chains in continuous time
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> CONTINUOUS_TIME_MARKOV_CHAIN </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> INTRO </LEVEL>
<TYPE> PDF </TYPE>
<MODULE> SOR3012 </MODULE>
<LINK> jim-chap25.pdf </LINK>
<AUTHOR> J.~F.~McCann </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
Notes on some examples of Markov chains in continuous time.
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> CONTINUOUS_TIME_MARKOV_CHAIN </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> INTRO </LEVEL>
<TYPE> XML </TYPE>
<MODULE> SOR3012 </MODULE>
<LINK> continuous-time-markov </LINK>
<AUTHOR> G.~Tribello </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
A video introducing the theory of Markov chains in continuous time.
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> CONTINUOUS_TIME_MARKOV_CHAIN </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> EXERCISE </LEVEL>
<TYPE> XML </TYPE>
<MODULE> SOR3012 </MODULE>
<LINK> continuous-time-markov-chains-problems </LINK>
<AUTHOR> G.~Tribello </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
Problems involving simple continuous time Markov chains
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
</PAGE>
