<PAGE>
  <TITLE> Exponential random variable </TITLE>
  <DESCRIPTION>


The exponential random variable is the continuous analogue of the geometric distribution.

This random variable has the key property of being memoryless meaning that the exponential

random variable $T$ has the following property:

$$

P(T>t+s)=P(T>t)P(T>s)

$$

The exponential random variable is the solution of the Kolmogorov equation for the two-state

jump rate matrix:

$$

\mathbf{Q} = \left(

\begin{matrix}

 -\lambda &amp; \lambda \\

 0 &amp; 0

\end{matrix}

\right)

$$

The probability distribution function for this random variable is:

$$

F_T(t)= P(T\le t) = 1 - e^{-\lambda t}

$$

while the probability density is:

$$

f_T(t) = \lambda e^{-\lambda t}

$$

The expectation and variance of this random variable are $\mathbb{E}(T)=\frac{1}{\lambda}$ and $\textrm{var}(T) = \frac{1}{\lambda^2}$



  </DESCRIPTION>
  <AIMS>
    <UL>
    <LI>  You should be able to explain the meaning of the memoryless property and why this property is important.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to write out a jump rate matrix for an exponential random variable and draw the corresponding transition graph.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to derive the probability distribution function for the exponential random variable by solving the Kolmogorov forward equation.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to write out the probability distribution function and the probability density function for the exponential random variable.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to obtain expressions for the expectation and variance of an exponential random variable by means of integration by parts.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to calculate the probability that event $X$ happens before event $Y$ given that the arrival time of both $X$ and $Y$ are independent random variables that can be described using exponential random variables.  
 </LI>
    </UL>
  </AIMS>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> EXPONENTIAL_RANDOM_VARIABLE </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> VIDEO </LEVEL>
<TYPE> XML </TYPE>
<MODULE> SOR3012 </MODULE>
<LINK> exponential-random-variable-video </LINK>
<AUTHOR> G.~Tribello </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
Introduction to the exponential random variable
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> EXPONENTIAL_RANDOM_VARIABLE </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> VIDEO </LEVEL>
<TYPE> XML </TYPE>
<MODULE> SOR3012 </MODULE>
<LINK> pairs-of-exponentials </LINK>
<AUTHOR> G.~Tribello </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
Calculating the probability that one exponential random variable is less than another.
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> EXPONENTIAL_RANDOM_VARIABLE </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> READING </LEVEL>
<TYPE> PDF </TYPE>
<MODULE> SOR3012 </MODULE>
<LINK> jim-chap18.pdf </LINK>
<AUTHOR> J.~F.~McCann </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
Notes on the derivation of the exponenitial random variable.
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> EXPONENTIAL_RANDOM_VARIABLE </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> EXAMPLES </LEVEL>
<TYPE> XML </TYPE>
<MODULE> SOR3012 </MODULE>
<LINK> exponential-random-variable-problems </LINK>
<AUTHOR> G.~Tribello </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
Problems involving the exponential random variable
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> EXPONENTIAL_RANDOM_VARIABLE </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> PYTHON </LEVEL>
<TYPE> HTML </TYPE>
<MODULE> SOR3012 </MODULE>
<LINK> exponential-random-variable-notebook </LINK>
<AUTHOR> G.~Tribello </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
EXAMPLE: project on exponential random variables
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
</PAGE>
