<PAGE>
  <TITLE> The geometric random variable </TITLE>
  <DESCRIPTION>


The geometric random variable is used when one is modelling a series of experiments that have one

of two possible outcomes - sucess or failure.  The geometric random variable tells you the number of

experiments that were performed before obtaining a sucess.  This random variable can thus take values 

of 1, 2, 3, ...



The probability mass function for the geometric random variable is given by:



$$

f_X(x) = P(X=x) = (1-p)^{x-1} p

$$



The expectation and variance for this random variable are $\mathbb{E}(X) = \frac{1}{p}$ 

and $\textrm{var}(X) = \frac{1-p}{p^2}$ respectively.



  </DESCRIPTION>
  <AIMS>
    <UL>
    <LI>  You should be able to explain what types of phenomena can be modelled using the geometric random variable.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to write out the probability mass function for the geometric random variable and explain how this expression is derived by using a tree diagram.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to calculate the elements of the probability distribution function for the geometric random variable from the probability mass function.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to show that the probability mass function for the geometric random variable is properly normalised.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to derive expressions for the mean and the variance of the geometric random variable using the condition expectation theorem.
 </LI>
    </UL>
  </AIMS>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> GEOMETRIC_RANDOM_VARIABLE </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> EXAMPLES </LEVEL>
<TYPE> XML </TYPE>
<MODULE> SOR3012 </MODULE>
<LINK> geometric-random-variable-problems </LINK>
<AUTHOR> G.~Tribello </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
Problems involving the geometric random variable
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> GEOMETRIC_RANDOM_VARIABLE </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> VIDEO </LEVEL>
<TYPE> XML </TYPE>
<MODULE> SOR3012 </MODULE>
<LINK> geometric-random-variable-video </LINK>
<AUTHOR> G.~Tribello </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
A video explaining the derivation of the geometric random variable
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
</PAGE>
