<PAGE>
  <TITLE> The grand canonical ensemble </TITLE>
  <DESCRIPTION>


The grand canonical ensemble is a statistical model that can be used to describe the behavior of a system

with a constant temperature, a constant chemical potential and a constant volume/pressure.  (In what follows

we will enforce constant a volume.)  If we have a Hamiltonian, $H(x,p)$, for the system the isothermal-isobaric 

partition function can be calculated using:

$$

Z_{gc} = \sum_i e^{-\beta H(x_i,p_i) } e^{\beta \mu N(x_i,p_i) }

$$

The sum here runs over all the microstates in the system and is replaced by an integral if you have a continuous

rather than a discrete state space.  $\beta$, meanwhile, is equal to one divided by the temperature, $T$, multiplied by

Boltzmann's constant, $k_B$.  That is to say $\beta = \frac{1}{k_B T}$.



The probabibility of being with an individual microstate in the grand canonical ensemble is given by:

$$

p_i = \frac{ e^{-\beta H(x_i,p_i)} e^{\beta \mu N(x_i,p_i) } }{ Z_i }

$$

We can thus calculate the average number of atoms in the system by computing an emsemble average using:

$$

\langle N \rangle = \sum_i N(x_i,p_i) p_i

$$

or by using the analytical result below:

$$

\langle N \rangle = \frac{ \partial \ln Z_{gc} }{\partial (\beta \mu) }

$$

There is a similar result that relates the second derivative of the logarithm of the partition function with the fluctuations

in the number of atoms:

$$

\langle (N - \langle N \rangle)^2 \rangle = \left(  \frac{\partial^2 \ln Z_{gc}(\mu,V,T)}{\partial (\beta \mu)^2} \right)

$$



  </DESCRIPTION>
  <AIMS>
    <UL>
    <LI>  You should be able to write an expression for the grand canonical partition function.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to write an expression for the probability of being in a particular micostate if the system has constant chemical potnetial, constant volume/pressure and constant temperature.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to explain how the grand potential and the grand canonical partition function are related.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to explain how ensemble averages are calculated in the grand canonical ensemble
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to explain how we can calculate the ensemble average of the number of atoms by taking a derivative of the grand canonical partition function.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to explain why the second derivative of the partition function must be positive using considerations based on fluctuations.
 </LI>
    </UL>
  </AIMS>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> GRAND_CANONICAL_ENSEMBLE </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> EXAMPLES </LEVEL>
<TYPE> XML </TYPE>
<MODULE> AMA4004 </MODULE>
<LINK> grand-canoncial-ensemble-problems </LINK>
<AUTHOR> G.~Tribello </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
An exercise on deriving the properties of the grand canonical ensemble.
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
</PAGE>
