<PAGE>
  <TITLE> Statistical mechanics of independent-distinguisable systems </TITLE>
  <DESCRIPTION>


In statistical mechanics the particles in the system are said to be distinguishable if the microstate the system is in 

is changed if the labels of two particles are exchanged.  The particles in such systems generally sit on lattice sites

much like the atoms in a solid.  These particles are said to be independent if there is no interaction between them.  

If a system is composed of non-interacting particles that are sat on lattice sites it is straightforward to calculate

the partition function as the $N$-particle partition function is equal to the 1-particle partition function raised to 

the power $N$.



  </DESCRIPTION>
  <AIMS>
    <UL>
    <LI>  You should be able to enumerate all the configurations in phase space for a lattice gas and for the adsorption gas on a surface.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to calculate the canonical partition functions for a lattice gas.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to calculate ensemble averages for lattice gasses.
 </LI>
    </UL>
  </AIMS>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> LATTICE_GAS </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> VIDEO </LEVEL>
<TYPE> XML </TYPE>
<MODULE> AMA4004 </MODULE>
<LINK> lattice-gas-video </LINK>
<AUTHOR> G.~Tribello </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
A video showing how the partition function for a system of non-interacting particles sat on lattice sites is calculated
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> LATTICE_GAS </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> EXAMPLES </LEVEL>
<TYPE> XML </TYPE>
<MODULE> AMA4004 </MODULE>
<LINK> lattice-gas-problems </LINK>
<AUTHOR> G.~Tribello </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
Exericses on calculating partition functions for model systems.
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> LATTICE_GAS </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> BLOCKLY </LEVEL>
<TYPE> XML </TYPE>
<MODULE> AMA4004 </MODULE>
<LINK> enumerating-exericse </LINK>
<AUTHOR> G.~Tribello </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
An exercise that will teach you how to write a program that enumerates all the microstates of a lattice system explicitly.
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> LATTICE_GAS </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> BLOCKLY </LEVEL>
<TYPE> GEOGEBRA </TYPE>
<MODULE> AMA4004 </MODULE>
<LINK> two-state-model-exercise </LINK>
<AUTHOR> G.~Tribello </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
An exercise on understanding the statistical mechanics of two state systems.
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
</PAGE>
