<PAGE>
  <TITLE> The partition function for molecular gasses </TITLE>
  <DESCRIPTION>


It is common to assume that there are no intermolecular interactions between molecules when calculating the partition 

function for a molecular gas.  Furthermore, it is also common to assume that the Hamiltonian for the molecules can be 

written as a sum of electronic, $H_e$, translational, $H_t$, rotational, $H_r$ and vibrational, $H_v$, parts as shown below:

$$

H = H_e + H_t + H_r + H_v

$$ 

as if the Hamiltonian can be written in this way the partition function can be written as a product of electronic, 

translational, rotational and vibrational parts:

$$

Z = Z_e \times Z_t \times Z_r \times Z_v

$$



  </DESCRIPTION>
  <AIMS>
    <UL>
    <LI>  You should be able to explain why the partition function can be written as a product of vibrational, electronic, translational and vibrational parts.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to determine how many degrees of freedom a molecule contaning $N$ atoms possesses and how many of these degrees of freedom are translations, how many are rotational and how many are vibrational.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to write an expression for the translational partition function based on your knowledge of the ideal gas model.- You should be able to derive an expression for the partition function of a harmonic vibrational degree of freedom.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to derive expressions for the partition function of a rigid rotor, a symmetric top an assymetric top and a linear molecule.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to explain what the equipartition principle tells us about the average energy of each degree of freedom of the molecule.
 </LI>
    </UL>
  </AIMS>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> PARTITION_FUNCTION_FOR_MOLECULES </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> VIDEO </LEVEL>
<TYPE> XML </TYPE>
<MODULE> AMA4004 </MODULE>
<LINK> molecular-gas-video </LINK>
<AUTHOR> G.~Tribello </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
A video describing how the partition function for a molecular gas can be decomposed in terms of translational, rotational and vibrational parts.
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
</PAGE>
