<PAGE>
  <TITLE> Ergodic Markov chains </TITLE>
  <DESCRIPTION>


A Markov chain is said to be ergodic if it has a limiting stationary distribution.

This limiting stationary distribution tells one the probability that you will be in 

each of the states of the Markov chain.  Hence, for an ergodic Markov chain with $n$ states

the stationary distribution is an $n$-dimensional vector of probabilities.  



The stationary distribution of a Markov chain can be found by finding the top (left) eigenvector of 

the one-step transition probability matrix using Gaussian elimination.  In addition, the elements of 

this matrix satisfy the ergodic theorem:

$$

\lim_{n \rightarrow \infty} \frac{M_i(n)}{n} = \frac{1}{\mathbb{E}(T_i)}

$$

where $M_i$ is the number of visits to state $i$ if there have been $n$ steps in your Markov chain and $\mathbb{E}(T_i)$

is the expectation of the return time to state $i$. 



  </DESCRIPTION>
  <AIMS>
    <UL>
    <LI>  You should be able to explain the properties that characterise an ergodic markov chain.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to determine whether or not a Markov chain has a limiting stationary distribution.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to explain the significance of the limiting stationary distribution.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to calculate the limiting stationary distribution of a Markov chain using Gaussian elimination.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to use the ergodic theorem to calculate return times from limiting stationary distribution.
 </LI>
    </UL>
  </AIMS>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> STATIONARY_DIST_MARKOV </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> EXAMPLES </LEVEL>
<TYPE> XML </TYPE>
<MODULE> SOR3012 </MODULE>
<LINK> markov-stationary-distribution-problems </LINK>
<AUTHOR> G.~Tribello </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
Problems on finding the stationary distribution of ergodic Markov chians
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> STATIONARY_DIST_MARKOV </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> READING </LEVEL>
<TYPE> PDF </TYPE>
<MODULE> SOR3012 </MODULE>
<LINK> jim-chap14.pdf </LINK>
<AUTHOR> J.~F.~McCann </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
Notes on the ergodic theorem and the stationary distribution of Markov chains in general
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> STATIONARY_DIST_MARKOV </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> READING </LEVEL>
<TYPE> PDF </TYPE>
<MODULE> SOR3012 </MODULE>
<LINK> jim-chap15.pdf </LINK>
<AUTHOR> J.~F.~McCann </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
More notes on the ergodic distribution and the stationary distribution of Markov chains.
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> STATIONARY_DIST_MARKOV </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> VIDEO </LEVEL>
<TYPE> XML </TYPE>
<MODULE> SOR3012 </MODULE>
<LINK> limiting-stationary-dist-video1 </LINK>
<AUTHOR> G.~Tribello </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
A video explaining the derivation of the ergodic theorem
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> STATIONARY_DIST_MARKOV </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> VIDEO </LEVEL>
<TYPE> XML </TYPE>
<MODULE> SOR3012 </MODULE>
<LINK> limiting-stationary-dist-video2 </LINK>
<AUTHOR> G.~Tribello </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
A video explaining why the limiting stationary distribution of an ergodic markov chain can be found by finding the principle left eigenvector of the transition matrix.
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> STATIONARY_DIST_MARKOV </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> BLOCKLY </LEVEL>
<TYPE> XML </TYPE>
<MODULE> SOR3012 </MODULE>
<LINK> ehrenfest-urns-exercise </LINK>
<AUTHOR> G.~Tribello </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
A programming exercise on simulating an ergodic markov chain.
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
</PAGE>
