<PAGE>
  <TITLE> Thermodynamic Potentials </TITLE>
  <DESCRIPTION>


A thermodynamic potential is a scalar, extensive quantity that can be used to represnet the thermodynamic state of a system.

The first thermodynamic potential you are typically introduced to is the internal energy and from the first and second laws

of thermodynamics we know that, in a system that can only do PV work, infinitessimal changes in internal energy can be 

calculated using:

$$

\textrm{d}E = T\textrm{d}S - P\textrm{d}V

$$

New themodynamic potentials are introduced by considering a system in contact with a reservoir.  Some important thermodynamic 

potentials include:

$$

\begin{aligned} 

\textrm{Enthalpy} &amp; \qquad H = E + PV \\

\textrm{Helmholts free energy} &amp; \qquad F = E - TS \\

\textrm{Gibbs free energy} &amp; \qquad G = E + PV - TS \\

\textrm{Grand potential} &amp; \qquad \Omega = E - TS - \sum_i \mu_i N_i

\end{aligned}

$$

The differentials of these quantities are:

$$

\begin{aligned}

\textrm{Enthalpy} &amp; \qquad \textrm{d}H = T\textrm{d}S + V\textrm{d}P \\

\textrm{Helmholts free energy} &amp; \qquad \textrm{d}F = -P\textrm{d}V - S\textrm{d}T \\

\textrm{Gibbs free energy} &amp; \qquad \textrm{d}G = V\textrm{d}P - S\textrm{d}T \\

\textrm{Grand potential} &amp; \qquad \textrm{d}\Omega = -P\textrm{d}V - S\textrm{d}T - \sum_i N_i \textrm{d}\mu_i 

\end{aligned}

$$

It is possible to use these results, together with the fact that all thermodynamic potentials are exact differentials, 

to relate all the thermodynamic variables to partial derivatives of thermodynamic potentials.



  </DESCRIPTION>
  <AIMS>
    <UL>
    <LI>  You should be able to give the definitions for the enthalpy, helmholtz free energy, gibbs free energy and grand potential.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to derive expressions for infinitessimal changes in the enthalpy, helmholtz free energy, gibbs free energy and grand potential.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to to explain what requirements are placed on the change in Helmholtz free energy for spontaneous processes in a closed system with constant volume and constant temperature. You should also be able to explain what requirements are placed on the change in Gibbs free energy for a spontaneous processes in a closed system with constant pressure and constant temperature.
 </LI>
    </UL>
  </AIMS>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> THERMODYNAMIC_POTENTIALS </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> VIDEO </LEVEL>
<TYPE> XML </TYPE>
<MODULE> AMA4004 </MODULE>
<LINK> reservoirs-and-thermodynamic-potentials-video </LINK>
<AUTHOR> G.~Tribello </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
An introduction to the notion of a reservoir and the thermodynamic potentials that we use to describe the state of a system in contact with a reservoir.
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
</PAGE>
