<PAGE>
  <TITLE> Thermodynamic variables </TITLE>
  <DESCRIPTION>


The thermodynamic variables are the macroscopic quantitis that describe the state of the system.  Many of these quantities can be easily mesaured 

or controlled in experiments.  There is an important distinction between <b> extensive </b> thermodynamic variables such as volume, which have 

values that depend on the number of atoms/mols that are present in the system, and <b> intensive </b> thermodynamic variables such as pressure and

temperature, which have values that do not depend on the number of atoms/mols in the system.  A system is said to be in equilibrium if the thermodynamic

variables that characterize the state of that system do not change over macroscopic timescales.  When two phases are in equilibrium the intensive 

thermodynamic variables that characterize state of the two phases must be equal. 



  </DESCRIPTION>
  <AIMS>
    <UL>
    <LI>  You should be able to give a description of the scope and applications of classical thermodynamics.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to explain what we mean when we refer to a system, its environment and the state of the system in thermodynamics.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to give a list of thermodynamic variables.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to explain the difference between intensive and extensive thermodynamic variables.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to write out and manipulate the equation of state for an ideal gas.
 </LI>
    <LI>  You should be able to explain the meanings of the following terms: isothermal, isobaric, isochoric, adiabatic, diabatic, isolated system, closed system and open system.
 </LI>
    </UL>
  </AIMS>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> THERMODYNAMIC_VARIABLES </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> INTRO </LEVEL>
<TYPE> XML </TYPE>
<MODULE> AMA4004 </MODULE>
<LINK> thermodymaic-variables-video </LINK>
<AUTHOR> G.~Tribello </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
An introduction to thermodynamic variables and the distinction between intenstive and extensive variables.
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> THERMODYNAMIC_VARIABLES </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> INTRO </LEVEL>
<TYPE> XML </TYPE>
<MODULE> AMA4004 </MODULE>
<LINK> work-and-heat-video </LINK>
<AUTHOR> G.~Tribello </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
An introduction to the roles played by work and heat in classical thermodynamics
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
<RESOURCE>
<TOPIC> THERMODYNAMIC_VARIABLES </TOPIC>
<LEVEL> INTRO </LEVEL>
<TYPE> PDF </TYPE>
<MODULE> AMA4004 </MODULE>
<LINK> thermodynamic-variables.pdf </LINK>
<AUTHOR> G.~Tribello </AUTHOR>
<DESCRIPTION>
Some notes describing intensive and extensive thermdynamic variables
</DESCRIPTION>
</RESOURCE>
</PAGE>
